Berta N. Briggs
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Berta N. Briggs papers
1908-1976
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Briggs, Berta N.
1.3 linear feet
The papers of painter, writer and educator Berta N. Briggs measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1908-1976. Found within the papers are biographical material, scattered letters primarily discussing her activities with various arts organizations, notes and writings, artwork including sketchbooks and drawings, scrapbooks, printed material, and photographs primarily of her artwork.
Provenance
The Berta N. Briggs papers were donated in 1977 by Mrs. Malcolm Fooshee, Briggs’s niece.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Berta N. Briggs (née Nabersberg) was born June 5, 1884 in St. Paul, Minnesota, daughter of John William and Rosina (Reinfrank) Nabersberg. After her graduation from Central High School, she moved to New York to study art at the Art Students League under Kenyon Cox, at the Pratt Institute under Ralph Johannot, and at the Teachers College of Columbia University under Arthur W. Dow.
Upon her return to St. Paul in 1905, Briggs was appointed the first Supervisor of Handicrafts in the public schools, a position she held for three years. From 1908-1911, she organized and directed the Department of Crafts at the St. Paul Institute School of Art and taught woodblock printing, leather work, metal work, and pottery. During these years, she attended the summer school of the Minneapolis Handicraft Guild, working under Ernest Batchelder and Bertha Lum.
In 1911, Briggs moved to New York to become the head of the art department in the Charlton School, a private school for girls, where she taught art and lectured on the history of art and architecture for two years. On June 18, 1913, she married William Harlowe Briggs, an editorial executive for Harper Brothers publishers.
From 1918 to 1928, Berta Briggs lectured on the history of art at Miss Chandor’s School for girls in New York. With nine other craft workers, she founded an outlet for craftwork, the Noank Studio Guild.
In 1928, Briggs began to paint landscapes and specialized in paintings birds. From 1930 to 1932, she was President of the National Association of Women Painters and Sculptors. She was Vice-President of the Society of Woman Geographers from 1939 to 1942, and was a member of the National Association of Women Artists.
Briggs’s book Charles Willson Peale, Artist and Patriot was published in 1952, followed by To the Shores of Tripoli, published in 1955.
Berta N. Briggs died November 12, 1976 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, writer and educator Berta N. Briggs measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1908-1976. Found in the collection are biographical material such as curriculum vitae and awards, and scattered letters primarily discussing Briggs's activities with various arts organizations. Notes and writings include notebooks for Briggs's two books Charles Willson Peale: Artist and Patriot (1952) and To the Shores of Tripoli (1955). The papers also contain artwork by Briggs including sketchbooks and drawings of birds, scrapbooks and printed material including exhibition catalogs and announcements, and photographs of Briggs's artwork.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms:
Subjects:
Peale, Charles Willson, 1741-1827
Subjects-Topical:
Women painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Women educators -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Sketchbooks; Drawings; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged as 7 series. Documents within each series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1932-1975 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1932-1961 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1950-1954 (Box 1; 19 folders)
Series 4: Artwork, 1931-1942 (Boxes 1-2; 6 folders)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1908-1968 (Boxes 1-2; 7 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1932-1976 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1929-1943 (Boxes 1-2; 4 folders)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1932-1975, Series 1:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Biographical material consists of curriculum vitae and awards.
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1932-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Women Artists Award Medal, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Association of Women Artists Award Certificate, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters, 1932-1961, Series 2:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Letters primarily discuss Briggs’s activities with various arts organizations, and include one letter signed by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Mabel Conkling, Gail Sherman Corbett, Elisabeth Sturtevant Theobald, and other artists.
  - Letters, 1932-1961, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Notes and Writings, 1950-1954, Series 3:; (Box 1; 19 folders)
  This series includes two notebooks concerning Briggs’s book Charles Willson Peale: Artist and Patriot (1952) and one notebook concerning her other book To the Shores of Tripoli (1955). Additional writings describe Briggs’s artwork and consist of typescripts by Briggs and others.
  - Notebooks Concerning Book Charles Willson Peale: Artist and Patriot, 1950-1954, (11 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-16)
  - Notebooks Concerning Book To the Shores of Tripoli, 1954, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-22)
  - Writings by Briggs, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Writings by Others, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Artwork, 1931-1942, Series 4:; (Boxes 1-2; 6 folders)
  Artwork by Briggs includes three sketchbooks of birds drawn at the Bronx Zoo, the San Diego Zoo, and the National Zoo in Washington, D.C. Also included are miscellaneous undated drawings, and a block print.
  - Sketchbook of Birds in Bronx Zoo, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sketchbook of Birds in San Diego Zoo, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sketchbook of Birds in Washington Zoo and Bronx Zoo, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings, undated, (see also Box 2) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Block Print of the Crucifiction, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Oversized Drawing of a Cat, undated, (see also Box 1) (Box 2 (sol), Folder 30)
- Scrapbooks, 1908-1968, Series 5:; (Boxes 1-2; 7 folders)
  Scrapbook 1 contains letters, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs and miscellaneous programs. Scrapbook 2 consists of only a few pages containing clippings. Scrapbook 3 concerns Briggs’s books Charles Willson Peale: Artist and Patriot and To the Shores of Tripoli and contains letters, clippings, a press release, and an exhibition announcement.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1908-1963, (2 folders; see also Box 2) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1950-1968, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 1, 1908-1963 (Box 2 (sol))
- Printed Material, 1932-1976, Series 6:; (Box 1; 12 folders)
  This series contains clippings including Briggs’s obituary, press releases, and exhibition announcements and catalogs that document Briggs's career.
  - Clippings, 1932-1976, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-44)
  - Press Releases, 1932-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1932-1963, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1939-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Photographs, 1929-1943, Series 7:; (Boxes 1-2; 4 folders)
  All photographs are of artwork.
  - Photographs of Landscape Paintings, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of Paintings of Birds, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Photograph Album of Artwork, 1929-1943 (Box 2 (sol))